So that's me. And then after graduating, like most Harvard graduates, I decided I wanted to join the WWE. So that's also me. (Laughter) Sure you remember me from Monday Night Raw in 2002 and 2003, and I had a blast playing what people affectionately like to call
Ese soy yo. Después de graduarme, como la mayoría en Harvard, decidí unirme a la productora WWE. Ese también soy yo. (Risas) Seguro que me recuerdan del Monday Night Raw de 2002 a 2003. Me lo pasé genial jugando a ser lo que la gente le gusta llamar
Chris Harvard, the Ivy League snob. (Laughter)
Chris Harvard, el snob de la liga. (Risas)
It was perfect for me. But unfortunately, I got kicked in the head by my colleague Bubba Ray Dudley, and I suffered a severe concussion. And it led to what became permanent postconcussion symptoms: constant headaches, inability to sleep, depression, feeling in a fog. And in that first year, I tried to figure out how could I make this pain go away. And I wasn't getting the answers I needed from doctors, and so I started digging into the medical literature. And I found there's this whole story about concussions that we weren't really being told. So I decided to write a book about it, called "Head Games: Football's Concussion Crisis" that came out in 2006. But in that process, I learned it's not really just about concussions. I learned about a disease called chronic traumatic encephalopathy or CTE. What we used to call punch-drunk, because we only knew about it from boxers. We knew that getting hit in the head too many times with boxers would cause their brain to essentially start to rot, to degenerate. And they'd have symptoms like memory problems and problems with cognition, depression, impulse control issues, aggression. So basically, I got ... I got injured at the right time, in which the first two NFL players were studied for this disease. And it turned out they both had it. The first was Mike Webster, 50 years old, already had dementia. The second, Terry Long, 45 years old when he took his life. The medical examiner in Pittsburgh decided to look at their brains and found this disease. I wrote a chapter about it, and I thought people would make a big deal out of it. But shockingly, even when the first two cases came in positive, there was never a national news story about this, what's going on in football with these cases of CTE. So the book comes out, not a whole lot is happening, and one day I read the newspaper -- November 20, 2006. I find out that Andre Waters just took his life. Those of you who know football, Andre Waters was someone I grew up watching. Former Philadelphia Eagles strong safety, [44] years old, a Division II football coach when he decided to put a gun to his head. In the article they reminded me, his nickname was Dirty Waters. He was known for leading with his head, so I thought I'm just going to look up did he ever talk about the concussions he had. And I found a quote from 1994 where Andre Waters said, "I stopped counting my concussions at 15. I wouldn't say anything, I'd just sniff smelling salts and go back out there." And I thought, I wonder if he might have CTE, too. If that might have contributed to whatever made him choose to end his life. So I ended up calling the doctor who did the first two studies, and I said, "Hey, I think you should study Andre Waters." And he said, "I'd be happy to. The problem is, the first two cases died in the county in which I work, and I could study them as part of my job. I can't do that with Andre Waters, he died in Florida. If you want me to study him, you're going to have to figure out how to get me the brain." So I said, "OK. How does one get a brain?" (Laughter) So I racked my brain and I thought, why don't I call the medical examiner who I think has the brain right now? So I called up the medical examiner in Florida, and I said, "Hey, you don't know me, but do you still have the brain of Andre Waters?" (Laughter) And he said, "Yes, I do." I said, "OK, are you going to study him for CTE?" And he said no, in fact at that time he didn't believe that was a real disease. I said, "OK, if you're not, do you mind if I have it?" And he said, "Well, young man, I can't give you the brain. You need his family's permission. But if you do get the permission of his next of kin, I will release the brain to you." And I said, "Great!" And then I realized I had to figure out who his next of kin was and ask them, and it turned out it was Andre Waters's 88-year-old mother. And I sat there, and I took a breath and I thought, "Am I really going to cold-call an 88-year-old grieving mother who just lost her son to suicide?" And almost everything in me said, "Don't do it. It's too much to put this poor woman through, she's been through so much already." But then this other voice in my head said, "You know what?
Era perfecto para mí. Pero desafortunadamente, fui golpeado en la cabeza por mi colega Bubba Ray Dudley, y sufrí un traumatismo craneal severo. Que derivó en lo que se convirtió en síntoma permanentes de postraumatismo: constantes dolores de cabeza, insomnio, depresión, dificultad para pensar. Y en este primer año, traté de descifrar cómo hacer para que ese dolor desapareciera. No lograba las respuestas que necesitaba de los médicos, así que empecé a investigar documentación médica. Y allí encontré todo este historial sobre traumatismos de los que no nos habían hablado. Decidí escribir un libro sobre ello, llamado Head Games: Football's Concussion Crisis que salió en 2006. Pero en ese proceso, aprendí que no solo se trataba de traumatismos craneales. Aprendí sobre una enfermedad llamada encefalopatía traumática crónica o ETC. Llamada demencia pugilística por conocerse solo entre boxeadores. Sabíamos que muchos golpes en la cabeza muchas veces entre boxeadores podrían causar que el cerebro empezara a degenerar. Y ellos tenían síntomas como problemas de memoria, problemas cognitivos, depresión, falta de control, agresividad. Básicamente, me lesionaron en el momento ideal, cuando se estudió los dos primeros casos de jugadores de la NFL y resultó que ambos tenían ETC. El primero, Mike Webster, 50 años, ya tenía demencia. El segundo, Terry Long, 45 años cuando se quitó la vida. El examinador médico en Pittsburgh decidió mirar sus cerebros. Y encontró esta enfermedad. Escribí un capítulo sobre ella, y pensé que la gente haría mucho revuelo. Sorpresivamente, incluso con los dos primeros casos positivos nunca se dio una noticia nacional sobre lo que pasaba en el fútbol con los casos de ETC. Así que el libro se publicó, sin pena ni gloria, hasta que un día leyendo el periódico, el 20 de noviembre de 2006, descubrí que Andre Waters se había quitado la vida. Aquellos que saben de futbol, crecí viendo a Andre Waters. El exdefensa de los Eagles de Philadelphia, de 44 años, era entrenador de futbol de 2ª división cuando decidó ponerse una pistola en su cabeza. El artículo me recordó que su nick era Dirty Waters. (Agua sucia) Era conocido por liderar con su cabeza. Pensé en revisar si alguna vez había hablado de los traumatismos craneales que tenía. Y encontré una cita de 1994 donde decía, "Paré de contar mis lesiones cerebrales a la 15ª. No decía nada, olía sales aromáticas y volvería a salir." Y me preguntaba si él había tenido ETC también. Si eso habría contribuido a ese final escogido para su vida. Llamé al médico que hizo los dos primeros estudios y le dije: "Creo que debería estudiar a Andre Waters." Y él dijo, "Me gustaría. El problema es que, los dos primeros casos murieron en el condado y pude estudiarlos como parte de mi trabajo. No puedo con Andre Waters, él murió en Florida. Si quieres estudiarlo, tendrás que descubrir cómo conseguirme su cerebro." Así que dije, "Bien. ¿cómo se consigue un cerebro?." (Risas) Me devané los sesos y pensé, ¿por qué no llamo al médico forense que creo que tiene el cerebro ahora? Así que llamé al médico forense en Florida, y dije, "No me conoce, ¿pero aún tiene el cerebro de Andre Waters?." (Risas) Y él dijo, "Sí, lo tengo" Dije, "Bien, ¿va a examinar su posible ETC?." Él dijo que no, de hecho, no creía que fuera una enfermedad real. Dije, "Bien, ¿le importa si me lo quedo?." Y él dijo, "Mire, joven, no puedo darle el cerebro. Necesita permiso de la familia si es de un pariente cercano se lo cederé." Y dije, "¡Genial!" Y me dí cuenta que tenía que descubrir quién era su familiar y preguntar y resultó ser la madre de Waters, de 88 años. Me senté allí, tomé el aliento y pensé, "¿Voy a llamar fríamente a una madre en duelo de 88 años quien acaba de perder a su hijo?." Y gran parte de mí, dijo: "No lo hagas. Es demasiada carga para esta mujer, ella ya ha pasado por mucho." Pero otra voz en mi cabeza dijo, "¿Sabes qué?
If guys are killing themselves from this disease and we could study it to maybe prevent this from happening in the future, sometimes you've just got to suck it up and do something that's very hard." So I called her.
Si la gente se mata por esta enfermedad y pudiéramos estudiarla, quizás prevendría esto en el futuro, a veces solo tienes que aguantar y hacer algo que es muy duro." Así que la llamé.
First time, nobody answered. Second time, no one answered, third... no voice mails. The fifth time, I got an answer. And thank God that Andre Waters's family was so gracious about the call and said, "You know what, we want to know what happened to Andre. We want to know why he changed so much in the last five years of his life." And so we studied the brain,
Primero, nadie contestó La segunda vez, sin respuesta, tercera...nada. A la quinta, conseguí una respuesta. Gracias a Dios, su familia fue cortés y dijeron "Sabes, queremos saber qué le pasó a Andre. Por qué cambió tanto en los últimos cinco años de vida." Y así estudiamos el cerebro
and it turned out that he did have CTE. He became the third NFL player diagnosed with the disease. This is what it looks like. He was somewhere between mild and severe. OK, we have three of three NFL players here. Maybe this needs to get a little bit more serious. Maybe something's happening here. So I ended up starting the Concussion Legacy Foundation, actually formalized the work, so it wasn't just some guy calling for brains. And I searched the world. And I put together the best research team I could find. So we partnered with Boston University, we partnered with scientists at the VA here in Boston, and we started a brain bank.
y resultó que él tenía ETC. Fue el tercer jugador de la NFL diagnosticado con esta enfermedad. Así es como se ve. Él estaba entre leve y severo. Tenemos a los tres jugadores de la NFL aquí. Quizás esto deba tratarse un poco más seriamente. Quizás algo esté pasando aquí. Así acabé creando la Concussion Legacy Foundation, formalicé mi trabajo y todo, así que ya no era el tipo llamando por cerebros. Busqué por el mundo y junté el mejor equipo de investigadores que pude encontrar. Nos asociamos con la Universidad de Boston con científicos de la VA en Boston, e iniciamos un banco de cerebros. Si quieres saber cómo curar enfermedades degenerativas, hay que empezar estudiando cerebros. En ese momento, éramos el primer centro del mundo centrado en ETC. No había sido estudiado formalmente.
And so we start this brain bank, and it's my job to get the brains for Dr. Ann McKee and her brain bank, right in the middle. We also work with Dr. Bob Stern, Dr. Robert Cantu,
Empezamos el banco de cerebros, y es mi misión conseguir los cerebros para la Dr. Ann McKee y su banco de cerebros, justo en el centro. También trabajamos con el Dr.Bob Stern, Dr.Robert Cantu,
truly my dream team of scientists that I support. So my job is to get the brains. And I was very successful in those early years. Since 2007 I've started every day by reading the obituaries. And it's a tough way to live. And it's hard on me and it's even worse on these poor families that I've been calling for the last 10 years, to ask for their brains. And so early on in the process, as it started to really eat away at me, I decided, you know what, can I find another way to get people to donate their brains to this research? And I figured out, what if we could create a culture of brain donation in this country? What if it became normal for athletes to donate their brain after they died? And so what I started was a brain donation registry. And I started asking athletes if they would publicly pledge to donate their brain to science. And it started with, actually, a hockey player in 2009. One of my first pledges was a former Harvard hockey player, Noah Welch, who was in the NHL at the time. It was a slow start people understanding what this was about. So when the news hit the front page, "Noah Welch pledging his brain to science," he said he went to the locker room the next day, one of his teammates pulled him aside and said, "Hey, I heard you're donating your brain to science." And he said, "Yep." And he said, "Wow. How many games are you going to miss?" (Laughter) True story. But we've been remarkably successful -- over 2,500 athletes have signed up. They get a brain-donation card they keep in their wallet. This is mine, I was obviously first, it says 01. And I will donate my brain to this. We've also been lucky to have people like Brandi Chastain, the women's soccer icon, NASCAR's Dale Earnhardt Jr. Just two weeks ago, Hall-of-Famer Nick Buoniconti who had been diagnosed with dementia, signed up to pledge his brain. So it's been wonderful, and the great thing about it is that it has worked in changing how we're able to get brains. So now, instead of me having to call, more families call us. And our phones ring off the hook. And so I can now focus on taking this information, figuring out how do we work towards a cure, how do we work towards prevention, and so my life has gotten a lot easier. This is just some of the headlines that we've able to get over the years from athletes pledging their brain. The problem has been what we learned. So when we started this, only 45 cases existed in the world of this disease that had been studied in brain banks. Since then, we have acquired 500 brains and found over 300 of them had CTE. To put that in perspective, the rest of the world has not studied 100 brains since we started this. What we've seen though is very frightening. So some of you might have seen the headline in July
realmente un equipo de ensueño que apoyo. Así mi trabajo es conseguir cerebros. Y he sido muy exitoso en estos primeros años. Desde 2007 he empezado cada día leyendo obituarios. Y es una manera dura de vivir. Es duro para mí y es incluso peor para las pobres familias a las que he llamado en los últimos 10 años para pedirles los cerebros. Al principio del proceso, empezó a carcomerme. Y pensé si podía encontrar otra forma para que la gente donara sus cerebros a esta investigación. Y pensé: ¿y si pudiéramos crear una cultura de donación de cerebros en este país? ¿Si se volviera normal para los atletas donar sus cerebros tras morir? De este modo empecé un registro de donación de cerebros. Y empecé a preguntar a atletas si prometerían públicamente donar sus cerebros a la ciencia. Y empezó, de hecho, con un jugador de hockey en 2009. Una de las primeras promesas era un exjugador de hockey de Harvard. Noah Welch, quien estaba en la NHL por aquel entonces. Fue un inicio lento que la gente comprendiera esto. Cuando la noticia ocupó las portadas "Noah Wlch promete donar su cerebro a la ciencia" dijo que al ir al vestuario al día siguiente, uno de los compañeros lo llevó a parte y dijo, "He oído que estás donando tu cerebro a la ciencia." Y él dijo, "Sep" El otro dijo, "Guau, ¿cuántos partidos te vas a saltar?" (Risas) Historia verídica. Pero hemos obtenido un éxito notable más de 2500 atletas se han unido. Han recibido una tarjeta de donante que guardan en su billetera. Esta es mía, obviamente la primera, dice 01. Y donaré mi cerebro a esto. También hemos tenido suerte de tener gente como Brandi Chastain, icono del futbol femenino, Dale Earnhardt Jr. de la NASCAR Hace dos semanas, Nick Buoniconti del Salón de la Fama quien fue diagnosticado con demencia, se unió prometiendo su cerebro Está siendo maravilloso, y lo grandioso de esto, es que ha funcionado cambiando cómo conseguimos cerebros. Ahora, en lugar de tener que llamarlos, más familias nos llaman y el teléfono se descuelga solo. Y así podemos centrarnos en recoger esta información determinando cómo trabajamos hacia una cura, como trabajamos hacia la prevención y nuestra vida se volvió mucho más fácil. Este es uno de los titulares que hemos tenido de atletas prometiendo sus cerebros El problema es lo que hemos aprendido. Cuando empezamos, solo existían 45 casos en el mundo de esta enfermedad que fueron estudiados en bancos de cerebros. Desde entonces, adquirimos 500 cerebros y encontramos que 300 tenía ETC. Poniéndolo en perspectiva, el resto del mundo no ha estudiado 100 cerebros desde que comenzamos. Lo que hemos visto es muy alarmante. Algunos de Uds. puede que hayan visto el titular en julio
in the "New York Times." And a recent study we published, that of the first 111 NFL players we looked at 110 were positive for this disease. Of the first 53 college football players we looked at, 48 had this disease. That's something that's a very big concern to me. And so now, I'm very much focused on what can we do to actually treat this disease? We still can't diagnose CTE in living people, we have no treatments that are going to be coming out of the pharmaceutical industry in the next five years. This is a long, long fight. But our Concussion Legacy Foundation is here to not only facilitate this work, and that's the long game, but the short game is, hey, we can prevent this. We can prevent this disease if we just stopped hitting people in the head so much. And frankly, we need to stop hitting children in the head. Turns out, it's not a great idea to hit a five-year-old in the head 500 times each year. And it does actually open up the door to this disease. And so, we've got a lot of work ahead of us. But I have great hope that we're on our way to curing this disease. But I hope you understand my story a little more now.
en el New York Times. Y un reciente estudio que publicamos, sobre los primeros 111 jugadores de la NFL que exploramos, 110 dieron positivo en esta enfermedad. De los primeros 53 estudiantes de futbol universitarios, 48 dieron positivo. Es algo que preocupa enormemente. Y ahora, estoy muy centrado en cómo podemos tratar ahora esta enfermedad. Aún no se puede diagnosticar el ETC en personas vivas, no tenemos tratamientos que vayan a salir de la industria farmacéutica en los próximos cinco años. Es una larga, larga lucha. Pero la Concussion Legacy Foundation está aquí para no solo facilitarlo es cuestión de tiempo, pero por lo pronto, podemos prevenirlo. Podemos prevenirlo si paramos de golpear tanto a la gente en la cabeza. Debemos parar de golpear a los niños en la cabeza. Resulta que no es bueno golpear a un niño de 5 años en la cabeza 500 veces al año. Ya que abre la puerta a esta enfermedad Así tendremos media batalla ganada. Pero tengo la gran esperanza de que estamos en camino de curarla. Espero que comprendan mi historia un poco mejor.
And now that we've gotten to know each other a little bit better, this is the time where I ask you, "Can I have your brain?" Thank you very much. (Applause) Thank you.
Y ahora que hemos conseguido conocernos un poco mejor, es hora de que les pregunte algo, "¿Pueden darme su cerebro?" Muchas gracias. (Aplausos) Gracias.